Guide to the State College of Washington Office of the President: Wilson Compton Records 1944-1952
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
State College of Washington Office of the President: Wilson Compton Records
1944-1952
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 160
State College of Washington. Office of the President
8 Linear feet of shelf space 16 Boxes
Records of the Office of the President of the State College of Washington (later Washington State University), related to the presidency of Wilson M. Compton.
The functions and duties of the Washington State University President are defined in University Faculty Manual, edition of 1987, as: In addition to being designated as secretary ex officio of the Board of Regents, the President as general agent of the Board is the chief executive officer of Washington State University. The President administers the policies approved by the Board of Regents, serves as advisor to the Board on policies and operations and is the agent through whom representations to the Board are regularly made. Other functions of the chief executive officer include: Leadership in developing policies and organization for teaching, research, and extension programs. Public administration of the University, including representation before the Legislature and other state agencies. Responsibility for the general welfare of students; the development, operation and maintenance of buildings, lands and equipment; financial matters pertaining to development, operation and maintenance of University; and the administration of regulations adopted by the Board of Regents. Responsibility, delegated by the Board of Regents, for all appointments, promotion, salaries, leaves, resignations, and dismissals. Presiding at meetings of the general faculty.
Wilson Martindale Compton was born in Wooster, Ohio and attended the College of Wooster and earned a Ph.D. in economics from Princeton University as well as a law degree. In 1916, he married Helen Harrington, and later had four children together. Compton became President of the State College of Washington in 1945, and remained in that position until 1951. His presidency saw creation of the College Senate, a first Faculty Manual, and establishment by the faculty of general education requirements in the humanities, social sciences, and natural sciences for all students, as well as honors at graduation. In April of 1951, in the midst of difficult financial times due to state budget cuts, the Board of Regents ended the Compton presidency. After he left WSU, Compton was Director of the International Information Administration (IIA), the forerunner of the United States Information Agency (USIA), within the Department of State. He died in 1967.
The bulk of the records are contained in the first two series. Speeches and publicity materials, including scrapbooks, make up Series 1, while Series 2 consists of correspondence.
Series 3, E. O. Holland, 1944-1950, consists of files that were originally removed from the office files by President Compton when he left the State College of Washington. He kept the files in his personal possession until his death in 1967. President Compton apparently retained these papers because they were potentially embarrassing to his predecessor, President Ernest Otto Holland, documenting as they do Holland's political and personal efforts in opposition to decisions taken at Washington State College, and to his "butting-in" from his position in retirement.
Organized in three series, arranged alphabetically and chronologically within each series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
When he left the University, Compton removed from the office files the documents found in the folder entitled "E.O. Holland, 1944-1950" (Folder 191). These he retained in his personal possession until his death. Later these were transferred to the College of Wooster Library with another sequence of his personal materials. In 1996, the Wooster Archivist transferred the documents to Washington State University Libraries.
The records were transferred to the University Libraries at some time before 1970. Certain of Compton's personal papers were added to the records at that time. In 1998, one folder of additional correspondence was transferred from the College of Wooster Library.
State College of Washington Office of the President: Wilson Compton and Charles Clement French Records, 1948-1956 (Archives 12)
Wilson Compton Day Books and Papers, 1928-1997 (Cage 810)
Claude Simpson Manuscript, “The Compton Years, The State College Of Washington, November 1944-September 1951", 1986 (Cage 5058)
Compton Family Dramatization Cassette Recording, 1947 (CT 9)
Washington State University Office of the President Media, 1937-2006 (Archives 328)
State College of Washington Office of the President: Letters from Prominent Correspondents, 1897-1951 (Cage 1616)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Compton, Wilson Martindale, 1890-1967 -- Records and correspondence
State College of Washington. Office of the President -- Records and correspondence; State College of Washington -- Presidents -- Records and correspondence
College presidents -- Washington (State) -- Pullman
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Speeches and Publicity Materials
  - "United States Mission to the United Nations." Address before the American Standards Association, October 14, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "An Adventure of the Mind." Address to Dr. Compton's first freshman class, September 17, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Strenghen Us for Noble Duty." Address to members of the freshman class, September 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speeches made by Dr. Compton to various clubs and organizations and organizations, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speeches made by Dr. Compton various clubs and organizations, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speeches made by Dr. Compton to various clubs and organizations, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles and speeches by Dr. Compton, 1944-1953
    - "An Adventure and a Challenge", Sept. 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Looking Ahead from Behind", Dec. 12, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Great Pilots Are Not Made in Smooth Waters", Mar. 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "College Gives You a Chance to Win an Education", Sept. 11, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Engineering in an Era of Big Science and Big Government", Sept. 9, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Keep Washington Green and Build for a Future", 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Our Feet on the Ground", June, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of State Press Releases
    - International Information Administration. #43, January 17, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Address Before the Washington Area Clergymen. #379, May 12, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Voice of America at the Water's Edge." #404, May 21, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - (Untitled) #730, Sept. 13, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Address before the Congressional Club. #57, January 30, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Waging the Campaign of Truth,", July-August, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles Concerning Dr. Wilson Compton. Includes a certificate from the Olympia Chamber of Commerce honoring Dr. Compton, April 18, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Improvements and accomplishments attained at the State College of Washington, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Inauguration of President Wilson Martindale Compton. Includes order of events, Program outline and Inauguration booklet, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning the regime and resignation of President Wilson M. Compton at the State College of Washington. (Gift of C. M. Brewster, Oct., 1955.), 1944-1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Material concerning the resignation of Wilson Compton as President of the State College of Washington. Statements by and about the Board of Regents and President Compton. News release items. 1951-52. Also contains program and speechess at inauguration of President Compton, 1945; Quarter Century Biography of Wilson Compton by Old Timer's Club. Newspaper clipping with pictures, 1945-1952 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (2 copies) of Wooster Clan taken at Princeton, May 9, 1964, with identification. Address of Dr. Howard Lowry at memorial service of Wilson Compton, Jr., at College of Wooster, July 16, 1964. Wooster Alumni Bulletin of October 1964, containing notice of death of Wilson M. Compton, Jr. Photographs of wedding of Compton's daughter at Pullman, circa 1951-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Inauguration of W. M. Compton as President of the College". Vols. I, II (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "The Inauguration of W. M. Compton as President of the College". Vol. III (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings re: resignation of Wilson Compton from the Presidency of Washington State College (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Series 2: Correspondence
  - Correspondence for 1945, A-B. Agricultural Economy. Mrs. Gordon Alcorn (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Advisory Board of Agricultural Sciences. Advisory Board for Technology (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Advisory Board on Technology, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Advisory Commission to the State of Washington Department of Conservation and Development, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Agricultural Chemistry, Division of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Agricultural Engineering, Department of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Agricultural Experiment Station, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Agricultural Experiment Station -- Tree Fruit, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Agricultural Experiment Station -- Western Washington, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Agricultural Extension Service, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Agricultural Sciences, Institute of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Agriculture, College of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Alumni Association, W. S. C, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Animal Husbandry, Department of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - vacant (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Agricultural Engineering, Department of, and College of Architecture, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Associated Students, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - B -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Buildings and Grounds, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Business Administration, School of, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - C -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Certificates of Merit, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Commencement, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Compton, Wilson (Dr.) -- Speeches, Articles, etc, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Athletic Council -- Earl Foster, Secretary, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Campus Beautification Committee, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Committee on Committees, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Committee on Courses for Veterans, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Committee on Curriculum (Special), 1945 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Committee on Curriculum and Catalogue -- Paul Landis, Chairman, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Committee, Faculty Executive, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Committees, Faculty, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Committee on Foreign Scholarships, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Committee, Housing -- Stanley A. Smith, Chairman, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Committee, Inaugural, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Inauguration, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Committee on Insurance and Annuities, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Committee, Appraisal, No. 1, 2, 3, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Committee, Scholarship Standards, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Committee, Student Activities, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Committee for Review of College Program, President's, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Committee, Veterinary Medicine, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Conditions of Employment, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - D -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Deans and Heads of Departments, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - E --, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Education, School of, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - F -- Forest Products, Forest and Range Management (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Faculty, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Farm Management and Agricultural Economy, Department of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Fine Arts, Department of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Foreign Student Scholarships, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - G -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - General College Extension, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Graduate School, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - H -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - History and Political Science, Department of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Home Economics, College of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Horticulture, Department of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Hospital Advisory Board, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - I -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Industrial Research, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Institute of International Education, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - J -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Labor, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Land Purchases, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Library, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Mechanic Arts and Engineering, College of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Military Science and Tactics, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Mines and Geology, School of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - M -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - N -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - P -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Placement Bureau, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Police Science and Administration, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - President's Office, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - W. S. C. -- Organization Notes, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Publications, Director of, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - vacant (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Q --, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - R --, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Radio -- KWSC, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Registrar, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Board of Regents, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - S --, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Scholarships, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Sciences and Arts, College of, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - State Department, (Washington State), 1945 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - State (Washington State) -- Legislative Material, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Student Book Store, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Technology, Institute of, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - U -- V, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - U. S. Department of the Interior, Bonneville Power Administration, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - U. S. Veterans Administration, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - U. S. War Department, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - University of Washington -- Dr. Lee Paul Sieg, President, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Veterinary Medicine, College of, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - W --, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - Washington State Horticultural Association, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Accreditation Study, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Associated Students, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Buildings and Grounds, Department of, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Budget -- Business Administration, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 122)
  - C --, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Committees, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Faculty Executive Committee, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Committee on Space Priorities, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Compton, Helen and Wilson, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - D --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - E --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - F --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Financial Information, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Fort George Wright, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Fraternities and Sororities, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - G --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - General College Extension, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - H --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - Housing, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - KWSC radio, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - L --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - M --, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - N --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - Orton Art Collection, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - P --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - President's Office Reorganization, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Q --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - R --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Regents, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - S --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 149)
  - Social Work, School of, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 150)
  - State of Washington, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 151)
  - T --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 152)
  - U -- V, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 153)
  - United States Senators and Representatuves, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 154)
  - W --, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 155)
  - X -- Y -- Z, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 156)
  - A --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - B --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - C --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 159)
  - Committee on Educational Policies, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 160)
  - Committee on Commencement, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 161)
  - Committees -- Miscellaneous, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 162)
  - Committee on Ten-year Plan for W. S. C, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 163)
  - Deans, Directors and Department Heads, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 164)
  - E --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 165)
  - F --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 166)
  - Financial Expenditures, Budgets and Legislative Requests, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 167)
  - G --, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 168)
  - H --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 169)
  - Hospital, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 170)
  - I --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 171)
  - J --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 172)
  - KWSC radio, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 173)
  - L --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 174)
  - Land Purchases, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 175)
  - M --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 176)
  - News Bureau, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 177)
  - Orton, Virginia and Charles, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 178)
  - P --, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 179)
  - P -- (continued), 1947 (Box 15, Folder 180a)
  - Publications, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 180b)
  - Questionnaries, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Registrar, Research, Retirement, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 182)
  - Regents, Board of, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 183)
  - S --, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 184)
  - S -- (continued), 1947 (Box 16, Folder 185)
  - State, Washington -- Legislative Material, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 186)
  - T --, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 187)
  - U --, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 188)
  - V --, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 189)
  - X - Y - Z, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 190)
  - The Drucker Collection of Oriental Art. (Box 16, Folder 190a)
- Series 3: E. O. Holland, 1944-1950
  - E. O. Holland, 1944-1950 (Box 16, Folder 191)